if we were to try to capture the
agnosticism
of Emmanuel Kant with respect to
Theology and metaphysics it would be
with the common expression that you hear
quote you can't get there
from here
Kant is famous for
building as it were an unscalable wall
between this world and the Transcendent
Realm
the wall is so solid so impregnable so
high you can't get over it so low you
can't get under it so wide you can't get
around it and so thick you can't burrow
through it
following up on another philosopher's
Theory whose name was Lessing
oh
who gave us the famous
metaphor of lessings ditch
where Lessing argued that the contingent
truths of History
cannot get you to the Eternal truths of
God you can't get there from here
well in this schema Kant made a
distinction that has perhaps been more
famous than anything else that he's done
and also perhaps more significant than
anything else that he's done and that is
he distinguishes between two realms the
one is called the numeral Realm
and the other is called
the phenomenal Realm
now the phenomenal realm is the realm of
Sensations it is the realm of
appearances it is the concrete material
realm where the scientist is engaged in
his exploration and in his inquiry
it is the realm where Sensations occur
so we might call it The Sensational
Realm
Sensational not in the sense of
fantastic we're exciting but Sensational
in a more literal sense in the sense of
it is the realm in which we have
Sensations or perceptions of physical
things
the external world to us
and the phenomenal world is basically
the arena of Investigation for the
scientists the scientist is exploring
and measuring and experimenting with
things that he can perceive
now the numeral realm is the realm of
metaphysics
and for Kant there are three things that
he puts in the numeral world that is
three
Notions or categories and they are God
the self
and what he calls the ding on zeesh or
what we would call essences
let's look at those in reverse order
what he's speaking about as Essences
are those metaphysical realities that
all of the previous philosophers have
been struggling with with their concepts
of substance or the substrate and
remember when we looked at the Lock and
Locke made a distinction between primary
and secondary qualities and then Barclay
challenged that saying that all
equalities were secondary and they were
and we remember Aquinas in his
distinction were Aristotle his
distinction between substance and
accidents everybody assumes that there
is some kind of substratum of reality
that exists beyond what we can perceive
that there are real Essences for Plato
those Essences were the ideas that are
the Eternal ideas for Aristotle they uh
in here in objects themselves
but whether you're a platonist or an
Aristotelian you still had some concept
of substance some ontology some sense of
being
but Kant is saying you never have a
perception of substance you never have a
sensation of essence or a being
all that we can perceive are the
external manifestations of these things
and so we can't know what that Essence
is in fact we can't even know that there
is an Essence that underlies these
perceptions
now that doesn't mean that he didn't
believe in Essences or in substances
what he's saying is we can't know them
he's agnostic about them
and that science cannot learn anything
about Essences so we might as well
abandon any pursuit of it and
metaphysics becomes more and more
speculative and less and less scientific
as long as it's trying to go to The Meta
realm to the realm Beyond physics into
the metaphysical realm trying to get to
this Essence now remember our study in
the history of philosophy began
with thales
and with the ancient Quest
for Ultimate Reality
basically what Khan is saying here is
that that Quest that has gone on from
time immemorial is a Fool's errand
you can't get there
from here
well
what about the self remembered Descartes
came to conclusion that the one thing he
knew with absolute certainty was that he
existed I think therefore I am
now Khan said yes but in order to get
there he's assuming
a causal relationship between his
thinking and his being
and he still never has a sensation or a
perception of his his own self
so that the self is something that is
speculated by Descartes on the basis of
a logical deduction from his thought
now I'll come back to that logical
deduction element for a moment but Kant
said that the he he he coined a phrase
to describe our knowledge of the self
and it was the phrase
the transcendental app perception of the
ego
this is one of the reasons why people
who aren't trained in philosophy have a
very difficult time reading Emanuel Kant
because he seems to be fond of creating
a whole new vocabulary and a whole new
language what in the world is a
transcendental Apperception of this ego
well again this is kind of an intuitive
thing where we have a sort of you've got
to have a sort of immediate intuitive
awareness of yourself as a self it's not
something that you can know
theoretically but you just go with it
sort of like the pure intuitions of
space and time that I mentioned earlier
but you can't penetrate to the core of
the being of the person
all you are left with are Sensations and
observed behavioral patterns and that
sort of thing you can't really get to
know
the self because the self remains
unknowable in the theoretical sense
but when we look at this division
between the numeral world and the
phenomenal world
it's not so much the self and the
Essences that have created the
consternation as a result of con
agnosticism it's the third concept the
notion of God
now
Kant grew up in a religious home
and he professed a certain belief in the
existence of God
but he said that we cannot prove the
with rational or scientific arguments
he said that the traditional arguments
the teleological argument which was the
one that impressed him the most which
was the argument from design that is
that this world manifests an incredible
pattern of design and purpose and
harmony
and such design
points to a cosmic designer how can you
possibly have design without a designer
and Kant his deathbed was very much
impressed with that argument but he said
it wasn't conclusive
because we're not sure that that design
is not something that we
are adding to this
experience that we're having
so that maybe we are the ones who are
imposing design with our own minds
and it's not something that we're simply
encountering
but the other arguments the cosmological
argument and the ontological argument
are usually distinguished from one
another
and the cosmological argument usually
means that you reason back to the
existence of God as the first cause for
the world that we perceive and that is
based upon cause and effect or on the
law of causality
so we reason back from this finite
contingent world back to an infinite and
independent Eternal self-existent being
as we've seen with Thomas Aquinas
you remember when we had a brief look at
Anselm that Anselm posed his version of
the ontological argument
and the ontological argument of Anselm
was recast both by Descartes and then by
a later philosopher by the name of
Christian wolf
and Christian wolf was the one that
can't critique most sharply
and he was he he basically says this
that all of the arguments for the
existence of God and the final analysis
come back to the ontological argument
they are arguments from being
and he says that his Kant says that
existence
is not
an attribute
and that fundamentally he made the same
argument against the ontological
argument that ganilo did against
Anselm's argument that in terms of the
idea of God there is no difference
between the idea
of a fictional God and the idea of an
existing God remember and when I when
Anselm said God is that which no greater
than can be conceived and it was and
gone alone said hey I have this
imaginary Island the most perfect Island
conceivable just because I can conceive
of a perfect Island does not mean that
that Island actually exists in reality
and and some replied by saying well
you're that's true with respect to
Islands but we're talking here about the
most perfect being
and that being cannot be conceived
as not being because if you're thinking
of it as not being you're not really
thinking of what we're talking about
here well Kant talked again about this
difference between a hundred guilders or
golden 100 dollars
imaginary dollars and a hundred real
dollars in terms of the idea of dollars
there's no difference
you still have the same idea of a dollar
whether it exists or doesn't exist and
so he he rejected ontological Arguments
for God and at the same time rejected
the cosmological argument for God
because he said even though he was
committed to the law of
non-contradiction and the law of
causality in that are necessary to his
categories to order the sensations that
we have
the assumption that is made by classical
theists is that those categories that
work and are necessary transcendentally
to sort out Sensations in this world
like the law of causality and the law of
non-contradiction without which you
can't sort out this mass of Sensations
that you have
how do we know that we can transfer
those things
to the metaphysical Realm
just because a raindrop requires a Cause
doesn't mean that we can move from the
phenomenal world where causality works
and jump over this
to the numeral world
because we have no perception of it
no sensation of it now to buttress his
critique of classical theism he also set
up a case of what he calls antinomies
that he says if you argue
philosophically for the existence of God
you run into irreconcilable
contradictions where you can talk about
free will or sovereignty issues of that
kind and one school of thought argues
for the ultimacy of human Freedom the
other one for the ultimacy of
sovereignty and those two are
incompatible and so that rational
speculation leads you ultimately to
contradictions
and because these antinomies persist
in philosophical speculation about God
you can't really know which one of the
poles of the contradiction
is true or
even if you can apply logic to this
Supra
metaphysical world
just because it applies here in this
realm Kant would argue does not mean
that it must apply up here
so with logic causality intuition all of
the things that we have we can't get
over this wall
now much of subsequent philosophy is an
attempt to smash that wall down
or somehow to get around the wall to
recover and to restore a ground basis
for metaphysics and or for theology
I've often said for example that Paul in
Romans 1 argues that God is known he is
known through the creature through the
creation through the things that are
made
Khan is saying you cannot know that God
exists from the phenomenal Realm
now I say this if I can be
transcendental for a second
if Kant is right
then manifestly Paul is wrong
and if Paul is right
then Kant has made an error
and I'm obviously convinced that Paul is
right and why why I've been a stick in
the mud with respect to classical
apologetics is that I'm saying that the
task of the Christian philosopher in our
day is to knock this wall down
and not just lie down and play dead at
the feet of caught but
but many theologians have abandoned
natural reason and natural theology
altogether because of the kantian
critique
Now quickly in the time that we have
left
though Kant
says we cannot know the existence of God
through theoretical thought
in addition to his critique of pure
reason he also wrote his critique of
practical reason
where where he kicked God out of the
front door of the Philosopher's house he
ran around to the side door into the
kitchen door and tried to sneak God back
in the back door
because he said even though we can't
know God theoretically
for all practical purposes
we must assume the existence of God
God's existence is a practical necessity
and to show that he developed his moral
argument for the existence of God and
again following his transcendental
method you've probably all heard of
kant's
theories with respect to ethics where he
talks about the famous concept of the
categorical imperative
kind of kant's version of the Golden
Rule
he says that it is the experience of
people to realize that everybody
has some sense
of hotness
some sense of Duty or what we would say
in simple terms some sense of right and
wrong
now again
he's not going to argue psychologically
for this where some psychologist might
come in and say well the reason for that
is that because the whole world's been
become neurotic as a result of Queen
Victoria or the Puritans or whatever and
that's why everybody has troubled
consciences
Kant wasn't looking at this from a
psychological perspective
again he approaches the question
transcendental transcendentalities okay
we all have this moral sense
this categorical imperative an absolute
sense of Duty
to do what is right
and he asked this question what would
have to be true
for that to be meaningful
or to put another way
what would have to be true for ethics
to be meaningful
and bottom line what he concludes is
there has to be a god
as Dostoevsky mentioned later if there
is no God
all things are permissible
because without an absolute standard of
righteousness
then all ethics become
our personal preferences either of the
individual or of the group who is in
power
but for ethics to be meaningful
ultimately
there has to be a standard and basically
Kant reasons this way for ethics to be
meaningful ultimately there must be
Justice
because if in the final analysis
the wicked prosper and the righteous
suffer and Injustice prevails there is
no practical reason to seek to be
ethical
because Crime Pays and Justice doesn't
so for ethics to be meaningful the first
necessary condition is Justice well then
he asked the question
what would be necessary for justice to
be real
well obviously we live in a world that's
topsy-turvy that's upside down
and Justice does not always prevail
so for there to be ultimate Justice
something else must happen there must be
life after death
you have to survive the grave there has
to be a personal continuity of
Consciousness or you can never
experience the full measure of Justice
well suppose you do survive the grave is
that enough to ensure Justice no there
has to be a judgment
and that judgment must be
perfect
and for there to be perfect judgment and
perfect Justice there must be a perfect
judge
and in the Perfections of that judge
that judge must know all the facts of
the case
all the uh mitigating circumstances
he has to have a perfect understanding
of every transaction before him if he's
going to give a perfect verdict but not
only must he have all knowledge
but he must be
righteous because you could have a judge
who knows all the facts but he's still
corrupt and could be susceptible to the
bribe so this judge has to be impeccable
in his character
but even that's not enough to guarantee
Justice because he must also have the
power
to implement his Justice he must have
the power to enforce the laws of justice
and as you can see before you know it
you have an omnipotent omniscient
righteous and holy judge judging people
and he says without that
there can be no grounds for ethics well
of course he said for practical purposes
for civilization to survive
we must live as if there is a God now of
course the Next Generation
the nietzsis of this world
came up and said okay
ethics
aren't meaningful there is no God
ethics are meaningless civilization is a
joke
let's face it and bite the bullet
and that's where we are
trying to be suspended
between
the meaningful and the meaningless
and as long as that wall is there
the only only thing you have is an
existential
you know hope that maybe something's out
there and that if you jump into the
abyss maybe God will catch you
but we'll look at the responses to Kant
as we continue later